Guide to the Zan Stark Collection M1816
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Zan Stark collection
circa 1935-1955
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stark, Alexander J. (Zan), 1889-1967
M1816
11.25 Linear Feet (15 boxes, 2 cartons)
Access to Collection
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in 2011.
Related Materials
The Marin County Free Library holds the Alexander 'Zan' Stark Collection, c.1933-1955 (http://contentdm.marinlibrary.org/cdm/landingpage/collection/zan) which contains negatives from his Marin County/Muir Woods/Mount Tamalpais series.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises over 3,000 real photo postcards and photographic negatives, a large portion of the output of Alexander J. Stark, a Mill Valley-based photographer who published under the name "Zan." Postcards and photographs focus on Northern California, circa 1935-1955, and depict scenes of nature, travel destinations including vacation & historical attractions, architecture, bridges, and various street & cityscapes. All images are in black and white, and most are captioned. Many of the postcards appear to have been removed from Zan's scrapbooks, and for the most part his ordering has been retained. However, most numbered series contain gaps or numbers used more than once, and images are also re-used with new numbers in some cases. Postcard numberings also may not relate to their respective negative, if present. More detailed descriptions of the postcards can be found below.
Biographical / Historical
Alexander J. "Zan" Stark (1889-1967) was a Michigan-born photographer who moved to San Francisco, California around 1914, where he established a photography and lantern slide business under the name Xan Stark, Alta Studios. In the early 1920s Stark produced at least three volumes of photographs of female nudes in an "Alta Art Studies" series. Stark moved to Mill Valley in the mid-20s and operated a studio at 324 Miller Avenue. He produced thousands of photographic postcards under the name "Zan of Tamalpais" through early 1950s. Zan photographed extensively throughout Northern California, as well as in Oregon, Nevada, Arizona, and elsewhere. He was the official photographer of the Redwood Empire Association beginning in 1936, and many of the postcards bear the Association's name. Much of his work appears to have been on a promotional basis, capturing roadside attractions, hotels, resorts & restaurants, and natural wonders such as Yosemite and the redwoods. Along with his son, Stark was also involved with local politics and journalism. Around 1953 Stark moved to Boyes Hot Springs where he remained until his death in 1967.
Postcards.; Photographs.; Photography -- California -- San Francisco Bay Area; Photography -- California.; California -- Description and travel -- Views.; Stark, Alexander J. (Zan), 1889-1967
- Postcards
  - #1-41 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    16 un-numbered postcards of Robles del Rio, California, one postcard numbered 41, captioned "Sphinx, Mt. Tam and Muir Woods Ry."
  - A (Box 1, Folder 2)
    "A" prefixed postcards of Southern California, especially Los Angeles, Pasadena, Santa Barbara, Balboa Island, and San Luis Obispo.
  - B (Box 1, Folder 3)
    4 un-numbered Big Basin
    1 un-numbered & uncaptioned man panning for gold
    B series B1-8, 12, 14-16 Monte Rio, Russian River B23 un-numbered Sebastopol
    BF series BF 1,2, 4-9 Bill Flynn's Top-o-the-World Ranch, Glen Ellen, Calif.
    BH 2, 4 Bridge Haven, Russian River
    BS series BS 1-12 Boyes Hot Springs
    Zan B1-13 (some un-numbered) San Francisco, esp. Cliff House, Sutro Baths & Pacific Curio Shop in Fisherman's Wharf
  - Bear (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Bear [Bear Photo Co.?] postcards numbered 500, 504, 505, 506, 507, 511, 512, 516, 517, 518, 519, 520, 523. Oakland and University of California, Berkeley
  - C (Box 1, Folders 5-6)
    Zan C1-137. Lake County: Austin's Resort, Adams Springs, Loch Lomond, Whispering Pines, Cobb, Middletown, etc. Some Zan-C numbers filed under "Hobergs"
    C1, 6-8 un-numbered, one captioned Coloma, Calif.
    C1, 13, 16 Castlewood Country Club
  - Composers (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Portraits of Western classical composers
  - C.H. and C.C. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Confusion Hill (near Garberville), Curious Canyon (AKA the Mystery Spot, near Santa Cruz)
  - E (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Zan E1-75 Petaluma, Sebastapol, Bridge Haven, Santa Rosa, Boyes Hot Springs, Sonoma, Glen Ellen, Healdsburg, other nature & coast
    EL1-3 Elk Creek Lodge, O'Brien, Oregon
    4 un-numbered Buena Vista Winery, Sonoma
  - G, H and Hawaii (Box 1, Folder 10)
    G3 un-numbered menu postcard, The Glad Hand, Sausalito G4 un-numbered menu postcard, The Farm Hand, Russian River
    aprox. 30 un-numbered Hawaii
    HS2,5,6,11 un-numbered California Hot Springs
  - Hobergs (Box 1, Folder 11)
    AKA Hobergs in the Pines.
    H2-36 (some gaps) un-numbered
    Zan C54-56, 69, 71, 73, 75
  - K and Lazy T (Box 2, Folder 1)
    K1-39 Mendocino County: Albion, Navarro rivers, Noyo Harbor, Mendocino, Little River
    KL 1-4 Kiami Lodge, Scottsdale, Arizona
    2-10 Lazy T Ranch, Joseph, Oregon
    Zan L99 Adam's Springs, Lake County
  - Marine life (Box 2, Folder 2)
    5 un-numbered postcards from Steinhart Aquarium, California Academy of Sciences.
  - Misc. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Many stamped or printed Ed Wood Post Card Co., Forestville, California. Includes Plymouth, Mass., Russian River, Paradise, Carmel, Robles del Mar, Clear Lake Highlands, Calistoga, uncaptioned motels, etc.
  - M and N (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Zan M1-20 Mystery Spot, Santa Cruz
    M358 Mountain Home Inn
    M402, 405, 408, 409 San Francisco: Cliff House, Sutro's, Playland
    Zan N1-72 Napa, St. Helena, Vallejo, Mare Island, Lake Hennessey/Conn Dam, Yountville, Angwin
  - MW and Mck (Box 2, Folder 5)
    "MW" un-numbered Mark West Resort, Santa Rosa
    "Mck" McKenzie Guest Ranch, Clio
  - R (Box 2, Folders 6-7)
    Zan R-160, 165, 167, 184, 195-198 Forest of Arden Resort, Redwood Highway, Miranda 201-219 Bodega Bay
    301-393 Calistoga, Mt. Saint Helena, hot springs, St. Helena, Napa Valley, Conn Lake, Beringer Winery, Angwin
    400-475 Clearlake Highlands, Lake County, Kelseyville, Clear Lake, Austin's Resort, Larson's Resort, El Cielito Resort, Edgewater Resort, Middletown, Whispering Pines Resort
    502-507 Russian River, Sonoma County
  - Richardson Grove (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Richardson Grove, Redwood Highway. 5 un-numbered postcards, four containing 4 images each and one possibly unrelated.
  - RR (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Rough & Ready, California
    RR1-26 un-numbered postcards, many reproducing historical images
  - S (Box 2, Folders 10-11)
    S1-201 Geyserville, Valley of the Moon, Glen Ellen, Boyes Hot Springs, Sonoma, Sebastapol, Russian River, Guerneville, Monte Rio, Jenner, Healdsburg, Bridge Haven, Rio Nido Beach & Resort, Johnson's Beach, Cloverdale, Mark West Resort, Santa Rosa, Mirabel Park, Summer Home Park, Cazanoma Lodge, Keefe's Cove, Hilton Beach, Drake's Beach, Cazadero Creek, Elk Grove Resort, Forest Hills Beaches, Forestville, Hacienda Beach, Russian River Terrace Beach, Tyken's Resort, Occidental, lumber, apple orchard, Roland's Beach
  - SF (Box 2, Folder 12)
    San Francisco Bay Area, 12 un-numbered postcards, four images per postcard.
  - Sherrod (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Sherrod Studio 1-61 Feather River, Paradise, Sterling City, De Sabla
  - Y (Box 3, Folders 1-3)
    Y2-426 North & South Fork of Stanislaus River, Columbia, Kennedy Meadows, Sonora Pass, Patterson Grade, Copperopolis, Angel's Camp, Dardanelle Resort, Jamestown, Knights Ferry, Pinecrest Lodge, Confidence, Strawberry Lake, Lyons Dam Lake, Pinecrest, Long Barn, Kennedy Meadows Lodge, Highway 108, Sonora, Tuolumne, Douglas Flat, Douglas Lodge, Calaveras County, North Fork of Tuolumne River, Vallecito, Tuolumne, Sugar Pine, Mokelumne Hill, Placerville, Hornitos, Sutter's Mill/Coloma, Diamond Springs, Fiddletown, Coulterville, Murphy's, Waterfall Lodge, Dorington, Calaveras Big Trees, Twain-Harte, Sparrow's Strawberry Resort, Silver Lake, Pilot Hill, Tyken's Resort, Russian River, San Andreas, Volcano, Kit Carson Lodge, Amador County, Leavitt Meadow Lodge, Bear Valley, Mariposa, Bagby, Kay's Resort
  - Zan 1-199 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Zan 1-11 plus one un-numbered: Confusion Hill Zan 59, 188: Yosemite
  - Zan 200's (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Zan 266 San Francisco
    Zan 296, 297, 299 University of California, Berkeley (see also 201-219 Bodega Bay in R series)
  - Zan 300s (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Zan/Zʃ 301-399 University of California, Berkeley, Lake Merritt, Oakland, Santa Rosa, San Francisco, Pacific Grove, Carmel/Carmel by the Sea, Monterey, Lake Idell, Glen Ellen, Monte Rio, Redwood Highway bridge over Klamath, Prairie Creek State Park, Petaluma
    Zan 330-339 Pacific Union College, Angwin
  - Zan 400's (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Zan/Zʃ 400-498 Monterey, San Francisco, Prairie Creek Park, Garberville, Salinas, Klamath, Old Hearst Ranch, Rancho Hacienda, Pleasanton, Redwood Highway, Hawleywood Heights, Eldridge, Tan Oak Park, Mt. Hermon, Santa Clara, Sonoma
  - Zan 500's (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Zan 500-599 Sonoma, Yosemite, Old Hearst Ranch, Pleasanton, Patrick's Point, Redwood Highway, Carmel-by-the-Sea, Eldridge Berkeley, Klamath River, University of California, Berkeley, Angelo's, Monte Rio, El Rancho Mesom, Willits, Colusa, La Honda, Cummings, St. Helena, San Francisco, Salinas, Prairie Creek State Park, Calistoga, Big Tree Park, Santa Cruz, Skeleton Park, Klamath Glen, San Luis Obispo, Pismo Beach, Crescent City
  - Zan 600's (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Zan 600-699 Prairie Creek Park, San Luis Obispo, San Francisco, Morro Bay, Redwood Highway, Yosemite, Wonderland Redwood Park, Old Adobe, Sonoma, Vallejo, Pismo Beach, Santa Lucia Inn, Salinas, Underwood Park, Skeleton Park, Clam Beach, Stewart, Nevada
  - Zan 700's (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Zan 700-792 Stewart, Nevada, San Francisco, Golden Gate Park, Hornitos, Yosemite, O'Shaughnessy Dam, Hetch-Hetchy, Vallejo Adobe, Sonoma, Eureka, Petaluma, Golden Gate Bridge, Cloverdale, Woodland Villa, Requa, Redwood Highway, Treasure Island, Eel River, Lane's Redwood Flat, Underwood Park, Wolf Creek Tavern, Wolf Creek, Oregon, Golden, Oregon, Nevada
  - Zan 800's (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Zan 800-899 Tan Oak Park, Reynold's Redwoods, Santa Cruz, San Francisco, Vallejo residence, Sonoma, Sacramento, Carquinez Bridge, Crockett, San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, Treasure Island, Beringer Bros. Winery, St. Helena, Redcrest Motor Inn, Highway 101
  - Zan 900's (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Zan 900-997 Jack London Ranch, Wolf House, San Francisco, Sonoma, Patrick's Creek, Riverview Ranch, Piercy, Santa Cruz, 17 Mile Drive, Vallejo, Martinez, Calistoga, Orick
  - Zan 1000's (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Zan 1001-1096 Monte Rio, Russian River, San Francisco, Merced County figs, Calistoga, Napa Valley, Mt. St. Helena, Laurman's Edgewater Resort, Clear Lake, Oakland, Dann Creek Park, Redwood Highway, Big Basin, San Francisco, Santa Cruz, Tan Oak Park, Santa Rosa, Sonoma, Fetter's Springs, Boyes Hot Springs, Valley of the Moon
  - Zan 1100's (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Zan 1103-1199 Sonoma, Redwood Highway, Eel River, San Francisco, Napa, Golden Gate Park, Santa Cruz, Santa Rosa, Russian River, Guerneville, Monte Rio, Guernewood Park, Calistoga, St. Helena, Veterans Home of California
  - Zan 1200's (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Zan 1202-1299 San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, Sonoma, Eldridge, Southern Pacific-Golden Gate Ferries, San Joaquin Valley, University of California, Berkeley, River Inn, Big Sur, Redwood Camp, Pfeiffer Grove, Carmel, San Francisco, Tan Oak Park, Redwood Highway, Pierson Wonder Valley Ranch, Del Pietra
  - Zan 1300's (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Zan 1400's (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Zan 1401-1499 San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, San Francisco, Golden Gate Bridge, Redwood Highway, Richardson Grove, Hornitos, Crescent City, Golden Gate Park, Klamath, Lane's Redwood Flat, Cedar Creek Bridge, Big Dam Creek Bridge, Lilley Redwood Park, Santa Rosa, Petaluma, Requa
  - Zan 1500's (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Zan 1500-1597 Golden Gate Bridge, Mission San Carlos De Rio Carmelo, Carmel, Rainbow Bridge, Carmel-San Simeon Highway, Del Monte Lodge, Pebble Beach, San Francisco, Mission San Juan Batista, San Juan, Monte Rio, Russian River, Rio Nido, Villa Grande, Redwood Highway, Richardson Grove, La Honda, Redwood Terraces, Sonoma, Eureka
  - Zan 1600's (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Zan 1600-1699 Eureka, Bull Creek Flat, Redwood Highway, La Honda, Boyes Hot Springs, Santa Cruz Big Trees, Ben Lomond, Cuesta La Honda Lake, Brookdale, Brookdale Lodge, Lane's Redwood Flat, Prairie Creek State Park, Richardson Grove, Monterey, San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, San Francisco
  - Zan 1700's (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Zan 1700-1739 San Francisco, Golden Gate Bridge, Golden Gate Park, Sonoma, Redwood Highway, Trinidad Head, Glen Ellen, Salinas, Carmel by the Sea, Point Lobos
  - Zan 1800's (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Zan 1802-1816 Five postcards of Yosemite, one portrait of John Muir
  - Zan 1900's (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Zan 1911, 1915, 1918 Yosemite
  - Zan 2000s (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Zan 2013-2043 Pismo Beach, Shell Beach, Morro Beach, Mission San Luis Obispo; Zan 2095 Wawona Tree
  - Zan 2,200's (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Zan 2232-2234 Weott, Redwood Highway; Zan 2265-2267 Pacific Union College, Angwin; Zan 2270-2288 Trees of Mystery Park, Redwood Highway
  - Zan 2,300's (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Zan 2306-2399 Grundy's Redwood Terraces, Redwood Highway, Eel River, Shangri-La near Willits, Cummings, Bishop Pine Lodge, Orick, Pacific Union College, Angwin, Prairie Creek State Park, Monte Rio, Russian River, Jenner by the Sea
    [note: postcards w/ 2300#'s are actually mis-numbered- they correspond to 2,300 # Series]
  - Zan 2,400's (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Zan 2400-2499 Monte Rio, Redwood Highway, Cazadero, Santa Cruz, Prairie Creek State Park, Klamath River, Mills Field - San Francisco Airport, Golden Gate Park, San Francisco, Golden Gate Bridge, Brookdale Lodge, Brookdale, Santa Cruz Big Trees, Shangri-La, Willits, Forest of Arden Resort, Miranda, Lilley Redwood Park, San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, Crescent City
  - Zan 2,500's (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Zan 741, K2, 4-9 (#2501-2509 negatives) Stanford University; Zan 2510-2596 San Francisco, Totem Pole Park, Crescent City, Pleasure Court, Willits, Unique Log House Museum, Garberville, Golden Gate Park, Armstrong Grove, Guerneville, Murphy's Guest Ranch, Villa Grande, Russian River, Shangri-La, Riverview Inn, Monte Rio, Angelo's Beach Casino, Prairie Creek State Park, New Hartsook Inn, Redwood Highway, Empire Modern Camp, Tales of Mystery Park
- Negatives
  - Negatives: A1 - E74 (Box 6)
  - Negatives: E47 - N57 (Box 7)
  - Negatives: N58 - S75 (Box 8)
  - Negatives: S77 - Y217 (Box 9)
  - Negatives: Y218 - Z410 (Box 10)
  - Negatives: Z411 - Z1030 (Box 11)
  - Negatives: Z1034 - Z1550 (Box 12)
  - Negatives: Z1551 - Z2270 (Box 13)
  - Negatives: Z2271 - Z2596 (incl. unnumbered and random negatives) (Box 14)
- Sleeves
  - Empty negative sleeves (no order) (Box 15)
  - Empty negative sleeves (no order) (Box 16)
  - Empty negative sleeves (no order) (Box 17)